It is
a privilege to be a detective.
Mark Birch: You deal with lots
and lots of horrible things,
that comes with the territory.
The majority of us
don't have to see these things,
don't have to
deal with these things.
The launch of the fifth
murder enquiry in such a
short space of time ...
Martin Brunning: Justice for
the victims is absolutely
the most important thing.
- You've been arrested
on suspicion of attempted
murder and murder.
- Could be worse.
Officer PTC: We can
only imagine the grief of
the families who lost
their loved ones in such
brutal circumstances.
- ... with your DNA.
How can that be?
- No comment.
Journalist PTC: The judge
said the murder showed a degree
of premeditation and planning.
He'd been stabbed and beaten.
Howard Groves: It was very much
a manhunt at that stage
of the investigation.
He knew that the
walls were closing in on him.
Stewart Gull: I always remember
a more experienced officer
telling me, you know, you,
you never forget these jobs,
and he was right.
VO: These are the detectives
who solved some of Britain's
most notorious homicides.
Now they re-live those cases.
Martin Brunning: Every fear
that I had was being realised
in front of my eyes.
VO: Through every twist and
turn of the investigation ...
Mark Birch: The only way you
forget about it is ...
is when you're asleep.
VO: Their personal accounts
reveal what it really takes
to capture a killer
and bring them to justice.
Howard Groves:
As a detective, you know, there,
there can't be any
greater honour than for you to
investigate the death - or
murder - of another human being.
Stewart PTC: It's often described as a privilege
to investigate the death of another human.
It's also a significant onerous
responsibility and whilst you
will always work as
part of a much broader team,
um, ultimately
the buck stops with you.
Stewart PTC: In 2006 I
was the Head of Crime Services.
I considered myself
to be a fairly experienced and,
er ... confident
leader and investigator.
But these circumstances that
we were being presented with,
for me, were unprecedented
and, and unparalleled in living
memory in ... in my county.
VO: In early November,
worried Suffolk mother Kerry
Nicol reports
her daughter Tania as missing.
Stewart PTC: It wasn't
unusual for Tania to sometimes
stay overnight with friends,
but she hadn't been heard
of for twenty-four,
forty-eight hours.
Mum became a bit more concerned,
she was unable to contact Tania,
and she, er,
reported her missing.
Stewart PTC: We were able
to track her final movements.
She caught the bus into town,
and we secured some CCTV
footage which clearly
showed Tania late on that night.
But from thereon in she
simply disappeared off
the face of the earth.
VO: Tania was only
nineteen and police
had immediate concerns.
Stewart PTC: There's
something not right here.
She had a mobile phone
and we were able to quickly
look at her call records,
which showed standard traffic,
both incoming and outgoing.
But from the 30th of October
you just saw a flat line,
the phone
had dropped off the network.
VO: There was another
factor that put Tania at risk,
one that not
even her own mother knew about.
Stewart PTC: There
was intelligence and evidence
to suggest that she was
working as a, a street worker,
a prostitute.
When you look at those
circumstances and the profile
of Tania you're already dealing
with a high risk missing person.
It's important
that we left no stone unturned.
VO: Early on in
the case one man repeatedly
makes himself
known to the police.
Stewart PTC:
He was really quite engaging,
quite candid with the officers
and indicated that he knew
Tania, that they'd
been together on a client basis.
He would regularly pick up
street workers and prostitutes
from the Ipswich area.
Stewart PTC: He was sort
of putting himself out there
saying 'You should show
some interest in me,
look at me, I knew Tania,
I'd been with her,
er, I'm clearly somebody
that you should be, er,
interested in'.
Um, which
was, which was quite unusual.
The surveillance team were
deployed for a couple of days
during early November -
mainly to assess his lifestyle,
just to try and build up
a much fuller picture of
the man that was,
um, presenting himself to us.
VO: But the surveillance
of this man produces no useful
leads and police
are no closer to finding Tania.
Stewart PTC: With each passing
day of course Tania is missing,
you fear for the worst.
You recognise that on the
balance of probabilities Tania
may well end
up being found dead somewhere.
VO: Then fourteen
days after Tania Nicol,
another local woman disappears.
Stewart PTC: Gemma Adams
was reported missing
by her boyfriend.
He'd driven her
into Ipswich, dropped her off,
and they'd agreed a pre-arranged
pick-up time during
the early hours of
the following morning.
So the boyfriend had,
had driven back in and had
waited for Gemma to appear
and, um, she didn't return.
Gemma was a prostitute,
she was a street worker,
she used drugs.
Gemma came from a, a
loving family, very supportive,
she'd probably just taken the
wrong turn early on in her life.
She was a little bit older
than Tania, she was twenty-five,
but they knew one another.
Stewart PTC:
Here we are now two weeks later,
still no sign of Tania
and we've got a second young
woman who's gone missing.
The concerns are heightened
and raised even further
at this point.
You recognise
the similarities.
We quickly assessed
her mobile phone records and it,
it showed a similar
profile to that of Tania.
Lots of activity, incoming
and outgoing calls and texts
up to the point of her disappearance and then
a flat line.
VO: Detectives ramp up the
search for the two missing
women with extensive
local appeals for information.
Stewart PTC: The disappearance
of two young vulnerable
women caused grave concern.
We feared for the worst
and we planned for the worst.
Stewart PTC: So as the Head of
Crime Management for the Suffolk
Constabulary it was my ultimate
responsibility to see that
we found these young women.
VO: For over a month
there is little progress.
But then comes
a terrible discovery.
Stewart PTC: I was at home
with my wife, it was lunchtime,
my mobile phone rang.
Um, and my deputy
told me that, um,
a water bailiff near Belstead, just outside Ipswich,
had found what, er, appeared
to be the naked body of
a female in the Belstead Brook.
News footage: I'm moving
leaves and bracken away,
saw the hair
flowing and the golden earring.
Right on the bend with her
head this end, facing upstream.
Suddenly realised that
I'd come across a dead body.
Stewart PTC: Our working
hypothesis was that
this body was one
of our young vulnerable women.
Stewart PTC: There'd
been significant flooding,
the terrain was extremely
heavy and muddy and I do recall
we needed the assistance
of a fire and rescue service
to actually retrieve
a body from the Belstead Brook.
You're automatically
thinking about forensic
opportunities, but of course I'm
already aware that she's naked,
she's in fresh water,
which is highly destructive.
So the potential
for the recovery of any forensic
evidence was, was
going to be ... very limited.
If, if not impossible.
Stewart PTC: The fact
that she was naked,
you automatically think
was there a sexual motive
to this untimely
death of this young woman?
Was the murderer,
in removing her clothing,
did he or she or they
think about that they were,
er, potentially
eliminating forensic evidence?
VO: Following a post-mortem
police put a name to the victim.
Stewart PTC: Within a short
period of time we were able
to establish it was Gemma.
The pathologist was unable
to determine a cause of death
at that stage, but certainly
confirmed in our minds that
we were now dealing with a,
you know, er, case of homicide.
Stewart PTC: We confirmed
that this was Gemma
so the prospects
for Tania weren't looking good.
VO: Specialist divers from
Norfolk Police are called in
to help search Belstead Brook.
For nearly a week
police comb the freezing waters,
hunting for anything
that might throw light
on Gemma Adams's death.
Stewart PTC: The soil was
heavily sodden so it was
really quite challenging.
But of course we wondered
where Gemma's clothes were and,
and it wasn't inconceivable
that we may have found them
somewhere within
the Belstead Brook.
VO: Six days later,
two miles downstream,
they find something
else entirely.
Stewart PTC: I do remember
distinctly getting a call to
say that the same dive-and-wade
team had come across a,
a body further
along the Belstead Brook,
and that was
believed to be Tania.
VO: In Suffolk,
the search for two missing
young women has become
a double murder enquiry with
the discovery of two bodies
in a brook near Ipswich.
Leading the investigation
is Detective Stewart Gull:.
Stewart PTC: It wasn't eve
on my radar that I thought
that we'd find Tania in
the same body of water as Gemma.
News footage: My initial
reaction was one of complete
and utter disbelief.
Your mind goes into
a bit of a whirlwind.
What's happening here?
How has this happened?
Tania Nicol - she too was naked.
We know that she'd been missing
for two weeks longer than Gemma.
Assuming she'd entered the water
at the end of October/early
November she'd been in
this water for, for much longer.
Stewart PTC: There was no
obvious injury to either Gemma
or Tania and the pathologist
was unable to give us
any cause of death.
What he did note was that, er,
both victims had hyper-inflated
lungs ...
which may have indicated, um,
some form of
interference with the airways.
VO: Determining how
the women died is not
the only difficulty police face.
Stewart PTC: We had nothing
other than two naked bodies.
Stewart PTC: We'd already
been investigating Tania's
disappearance for five weeks and
Gemma's for a little over two,
and we'd recovered
little or no evidence.
This increases the challenge,
the professional challenge
to finding those responsible.
Stewart PTC: Were we
looking for the same person
or persons here?
We didn't know at this stage
but the similarities were,
you know, were striking.
VO: As detectives struggle
with the lack of trace evidence,
news of the young women's
deaths is sending shock
waves across the county.
Stewart PTC: Suffolk is
one of the safest places
to live in the UK.
We would experience on
average somewhere between six
and seven murder investigations
during the course of the year.
Incidents of this
nature are very rare.
Certainly unprecedented
in living memory as far
as Suffolk was concerned.
VO: Street workers in
Ipswich red light district
are particularly anxious.
And particularly at risk.
Reporter: Why have you
decided to come out tonight?
'Cause I need the money.
I need the money.
You know.
Despite the dangers?
Well ... it has made me a bit
wary about getting into cars,
you know.
But presumably you,
you will do that tonight?
Woman: Well, probably.
VO: Then just two days
after Tania there's
another shocking find.
Stewart PTC: I was ironing
my shirts for the forthcoming
week and the phone rang and
it was the Force Control Room.
Stewart PTC: They told me
a motorist had driven through
the village of Nacton, which
is just to the south of Ipswich,
and the driver had seen what
initially they had thought was
a mannequin lying in a wooded
area, er, just off the road.
But on closer examination
they realised that this was
the naked body of a female.
Stewart PTC: We weren't
looking for anybody else,
who on earth is this latest,
er, victim that's been found?
I think that was probably
one of the lowest moments
in my sort of professional
life because you
just begin to think 'Good grief, what on earth is going on here?'
VO: At first there's little
to connect the bodies found
in the Belstead Brook with
the new discovery at Nacton.
Stewart PTC:
She wasn't found in water,
unlike Gemma and Tania.
She was on dry land.
Stewart PTC: She appeared
to have been laid out in
a cruciform position.
She had long peroxide blonde
hair that was drawn back
in a conical form.
Whoever had taken her to this
place appeared to have spent
some time with her, you
know, she wasn't just dumped.
Stewart PTC: She
was some distance from the road,
twenty or thirty metres.
The murderer - he or she
- certainly hadn't gone to
any lengths to cover her
up or bury her, disguise her in,
in undergrowth
so it was a little odd.
She had some quite distinctive
tattoos on her upper arm.
Those tattoos
provided us with a name.
And the name
was Anneli Alderton.
VO: With the light fading
Detective Gull has to make
a difficult decision.
Stewart PTC: You only
get one go at a crime scene.
Once you walk away, it's gone.
It was now dark, wet and windy
so we wanted to lift her in
daylight in order to maximise
the potential for the recovery
of any forensic evidence.
We agreed that we would leave
her laying there overnight.
That was ... a really difficult
decision because of course,
having established her identity,
we needed to tell her family
that that's
what we was going to, to do.
And I suspect her family
probably got little sleep that
night knowing that their loved
one was laying where she was.
But that was
the right thing to do.
VO: Details emerge more
clearly connecting 24-year-old
Anneli with the
first two victims.
Stewart PTC: Anneli had
a similar profile to
that of Tania and Gemma.
She was young,
she had been a street worker,
a prostitute on and off.
There was some intelligence
to indicate that she had
or was using illicit
drugs so a very young
and vulnerable female.
Stewart PTC: We used
Doctor Nat Cary, the same home,
Home Office pathologist
and I think it was for
the first time with
this victim he was able
to establish a,
a cause of death.
There'd been some form of
interference of, er, her airway.
She also had hyper-inflated
lungs so very similar to
the condition that, er,
Gemma and Tania had been found.
Newsreader: Good afternoon.
Police are investigating
the possibility that a serial
killer could be at large
in Ipswich following
the discovery of
the body of a third prostitute
on the outskirts of the city.
Stewart PCT And it began
to feel like a crime in action.
It's a term that
we use ordinarily just for, er,
kidnaps or demands where
the crime is actually happening.
It means you need to respond
with some speed otherwise
somebody's going to get harmed.
And of course in these
circumstances we feared that
there may be further victims.
VO: Racing against
time to prevent another murder,
Stewart's
team is stretched to capacity.
Stewart PTC: Suffolk is
one of the smallest forces
in England and Wales.
In terms of resources
and specialists ... we were
beginning to be stretched.
We were at close
to tipping point.
Support from our immediate
neighbours in Norfolk
and Cambridgeshire
was offered and we accepted.
It very quickly escalated.
A total of additional three
hundred officers and staff
who came to our support.
VO: For the police,
the pressure is being felt
from all directions.
Stewart PTC: This
was no longer a local story.
We had media organisations right
from around the world reporting
and following the events.
I can recall the media
saying 'Is the murderer
toying with you?
Is he playing with you?'
Er, these three victims
were only a stone's throw form,
a few miles from
Suffolk Police Headquarters.
VO: New developments mean
that pressure is only
going to increase.
Stewart PTC: Following the
discovery of Anneli Alderton,
we quickly become aware that
during the following
twenty-four hours, er,
two other, er, young women,
er, of a similar profile to
the first three are reported
as missing.
And they're Paula
Clennell and Annette Nicholls.
Stewart PTC: So we knew
the clock was ticking
and it was ticking quickly.
In Suffolk, Detective Stewart Gull: is leading a
major murder enquiry.
The killer
is targeting street workers.
Three bodies have already been
found and now two more young
women are missing.
Stewart PTC: I can remember
appealing specifically
for these two young
women to make contact with us.
Or anybody who may
have known their whereabouts.
VO: Police warn women in
Ipswich to stay in for
their own safety.
News footage: Assistant Chief
Constable Jacqui Cheer Please
stay off the streets.
If you are out alone at night
you are putting yourself
in danger at this time.
VO: Fear is
spreading throughout
the wider community too.
Reporter PTC: Everybody
here you talk to has
the same thought.
People are terrified.
Female interviewee: Normally
I ... I'd walk around
on my own but, um,
at the moment 'cause it's quite,
it's quite
scary so I've had to get, um,
my boyfriend
to come and meet me today.
VO: Within twenty-four
hours the fear and shock
consuming Ipswich
reaches a whole new level.
Stewart Gull:: At 3.05 p.m.
today police received a call
from a member of the public
who was walking along
the old Felixstowe Road
near the Levington turnoff.
He saw what appeared to
be the naked body of a female,
about twenty feet off the road.
Police immediately attended
and have closed the road and
have set up a cordon.
As part of our initial
response the helicopter was
sent up to film the scene.
Pilot: - Foxtrot-One-Sierra
from Alpha-Nine-Nine.
- Alpha-Nine-Nine go ahead.
- Yeah, unfortunately we've,
looks like we've found
a second body in the woodland.
Um, it's approximately two
hundred yards and probably
the same distance
in as the first.
Stewart PTC: Within the space
of ten minutes not only have
we now got a fourth
victim, but we've got a fifth.
So if there'd been difficult
and dark moments earlier in
the investigation, goodness only
knows what this place was now.
Stewart Gull: I can confirm
that this afternoon,
Tuesday December the twelfth,
two bodies have been
found near Ipswich.
This is breaking news and we're
giving it to you as we get it.
Stewart PTC: I'm
not sure who was more aghast,
the media and
the public or ourselves.
I thought at one stage
my heart was going to
jump out through the chest.
VO: The bodies are quickly
identified as those of
the women reported
missing the previous day.
VO: Annette
Nicholls was twenty-nine.
She had an 8-year-old child
and she was known as a
street worker in Ipswich.
Stewart PTC: Annette
had been laid out in a cruciform
position, the same as Anneli,
with her hair pulled back.
VO: The other body found at
Levington is confirmed as that
of 24-year-old Paula Clennell.
The way her body had been
left is altogether different.
Stewart PTC: Paula had just
been dumped, just crumpled.
She literally had just been sort
of tossed into the undergrowth.
Probably because when
the murderer deposited her there
police colleagues were
already on the scene in
Nacton at Anneli
Alderton's find.
Stewart PTC:
And I think he, she,
they decided that they couldn't
spend the time that perhaps they
had with Anneli and Annette,
and that's why Paula was
just dumped in
the way that she was.
VO: Investigations into
Paula's last known movements
bring a chilling realisation.
Stewart PTC: The media,
understandably as part of their
reporting and their story,
looked to speak with a number
of street workers and,
er, one of those who was, er,
interviewed was ... was Paula.
Reporter: Woman: Why have
you decided to come out tonight?
'Cause I need the money.
Stewart PTC: And she of course
recognised the vulnerability
and the danger
in what she did.
She also articulated that she
didn't feel she had a choice.
VO: Paula had been interviewed
about a killer on the loose
and days later
she had become a victim herself.
Stewart PTC: The
post-mortems of both Paula
and Annette were subsequently
undertaken by the same
pathologist, and again
he was able to establish a,
a similar cause
of death to that of Anneli.
An interference
of the, the airways,
of some form of strangulation.
Um, and they too had
hyper-inflated lungs so that
was now the consistent
sort of presenting factor,
er, in terms of, in terms
of all five deceased victims.
VO: Five women with shared
backgrounds in life are now
connected in death.
Reporter: It is inconceivable
surely that these five murders
are not the work of one man.
So Suffolk Police, one of
Britain's smallest rural forces,
is now dealing with one
of the country's biggest
serial murder hunts.
Stewart PTC: With every
additional victim it just
adds another level of
severity, complexity, challenge.
All five victims were
found during the course
of a ten-day period.
We've got a serial
killer on the loose.
It really provided for
a focus and an internal
pressure on needing to
find the individual or
individuals as
quickly as possible.
Fiona Bruce: Whoever's
responsible - is still
out there.
He's left precious few clues as
to his identity and the police
desperately need a breakthrough.
Stewart PTC: There was
a tremendous response from the
public and the local community,
certainly as things escalated
that week following the
discovery of Paula and Annette.
Stewart PTC:
Whilst that's great,
of course logistically
that presents a, er,
as a challenge to you.
Was there a golden nugget in
amongst the information that you
get form the public?
We needed a, a huge team
just to be able to manage that.
The overall challenge
was just the sheer pace,
the sheer sort of breadth
and depth of what we
were dealing with.
Jon Snow: Five women
found dead in the last ten days.
The hunt for the killer
has become the biggest murder
investigation ever carried
out by East Anglian Police
of any county.
VO: Despite the huge police
investigation there is still
no key to solving the murders.
VO: The only suspect
detectives have is the man who
put himself in the frame right
at the start of the enquiry.
Stewart PTC: He said 'Well
if I was you, I'd suspect me'.
He was really
quite a strange individual.
VO: Once more police
put him under surveillance.
Stewart PTC:
I can remember, er, getting
a call late one evening
from the ground command to
say 'We're behind him.
He's just picked up a street
worker and he's driving
out of Ipswich,
what do you want us to do?'
Put yourself in my shoes.
What would you do?
We already
had a number of homicides,
was this
the potential for another one?
Of course it was.
We had some drugs
intelligence and we used that
as a ruse to stop
him and separate both parties.
Ultimately to protect her.
VO: The little evidence
available so far has been
purely circumstantial.
But now the Forensic Science
Services drops a bombshell.
Stewart PTC: I was actually
grabbing a bite to eat, um,
it was about seven o'clock
in the evening in the canteen,
I was with my deputy.
And I can remember
the scientific services' manager
David Stagg walking up
to me and saying 'Stewart, er,
I've got some information that I
think you'll be interested in'.
And it transpired that from all
three of the victims that were
found on the land - so Anneli,
Paula and Annette - that a DNA
profile had been recovered
from all three victims.
And it was the same person.
And I can remember David
saying to me 'Well don't
you want to
know who it is?'
He said,
'It's Steve Wright'.
So a man by
the name of Steve Wright.
I think I said
'Who the hell is Steve Wright?'
VO: Police
are hunting for the killer
or killers
of five women in Suffolk.
Three of their bodies have
revealed compelling DNA
evidence pointing
to local man Steve Wright.
Stewart PTC: We had his
profile on all three victims
so this was a most significant,
er, breakthrough in terms
of the investigation.
VO: Detective Gull has
to make a high risk call-
whether to arrest
Steve Wright now, or wait.
Stewart PTC: We were confident that he was Involved,
but was he primarily Involved
or was he just an accomplice?
And that's why we took the
decision to arrest him 48 hours
later, put him under
surveillance in the intervening
period to allow us to do
the necessary planning before we
went and knocked on his door.
It was
still a big decision to make,
not to go and
arrest Steve Wright immediately.
The risk of allowing him further
freedom was probably as high as
it could be, but
we didn't feel we were ready,
we needed a little bit more time
to plan for his arrest and learn
as much about him as we could.
VO: The DNA evidence only
linked Steve Wright to the three
women found on dry land,
so the team's original
suspect remains
of significant interest.
Stewart PTC:
We couldn't just ignore him.
We didn't know at that stage
whether in fact Wright
and this man weren't
working together as a team.
VO: Police arrest
their first male suspect
on suspicion of murder.
While he's questioned
detectives build a profile
of their newest suspect,
Steve Wright.
Stewart PTC: We established
that he lived on London Road
in the heart of the
red light district in Ipswich.
He appeared to have a partner.
She was always
working nights in a call centre.
He worked at a foundry
as a fork-lift truck driver
He'd been stop-checked on
a couple of occasions in respect
to both Tania's
and Gemma's disappearance.
He'd been subject
to house-to-house enquiries.
We'd got a questionnaire that
he'd completed and interestingly
we were able to establish
that he'd, he'd lied to us,
he'd lied to us through
the questionnaire
and on the road-check.
VO: Police attention would not
have been drawn to 48-year-old
Wright if it hadn't been
for a minor crime in his past.
Stewart We had dealt
with Steve Wright back in 2001.
He was employed as a
barman in a hotel at Felixstowe.
He'd stolen some cash from
the till and as we do with all
individuals who are charged
with offences of this nature,
we secure a DNA profile.
So Steve Wright's profile
was already on the national
DNA database.
VO: What the DNA evidence
doesn't provide is proof
of Wright's
Involvement in all five murders.
The team
hone in on his recent movements.
Stewart PTC: His vehicle
had been captured on ANPR -
Automatic Number Plate
Recognition - driving out of
Ipswich on the nights of
the disappearance of both
Tania and Anneli.
Not only have we got these, er,
his DNA on the three victims,
but we've also got these
other elements now that
increasingly make
him as our number one suspect.
Stewart Gull:: A
48-year-old man was arrested
at his home address in Ipswich
at approximately
five a.m. this morning.
He has been arrested on
suspicion of murdering
all five women.
Stewart PTC: At the point of
arrest he had a big wobble
and he virtually collapsed.
Because he knows,
um, his game is up.
VO: In custody, however,
Steve Wright gives little away.
Stewart PTC: Throughout his
detention pretty unemotional,
pretty detached,
maybe a bit arrogant.
Officer: This is your earliest
opportunity to give an account
and that is significant
'cause it makes a difference.
We've got the last girl to
go missing with your DNA
and the one before with your
DNA both on their naked bodies.
How can that be?
Wright: No comment.
VO: Throughout eight hours
of questioning Steve Wright
simply answers 'No comment'.
Despite this, the Crown Prosecution Service agree
there's enough
evidence to progress.
Newsreader: In the last
few minutes Suffolk Police have
announced they have charged
a man with the murder of five
prostitutes in Ipswich.
He is Steve Wright,
the second man to be arrested.
VO: Police are satisfied that
their initial suspect is not
Involved in the murders
and release him without charge.
Steve Wright's trial date
is then set for January 2008,
a full year ahead.
Stewart PTC: I think there's
a perception that as soon as
you've made an arrest,
and certainly charged,
you've got your man.
Job done.
But as I tell all my teams,
that's when the hard work begins
because we now have
responsibility for building
a successful prosecution case.
Nobody else is going
to do it, it's going to be us.
News footage: We forensically
dismantled Steve Wright's house.
We took away a lot
of clothing, took away his car.
On his fluorescent jacket there
were traces of blood from both
Annette and Paula.
VO: Wright's Ford Mondeo
also delivers droplets
of Paula's blood.
Stewart VO: How on earth
has Paula's blood ended up on
the back seat of his car?
VO: But police are still
lacking forensic evidence
firmly connecting Wright
to Gemma Adams and Tania Nicol.
Stewart VO: When Tania and
Gemma were recovered from the
Belstead Brook the chances of
recovering any forensic evidence
was going to be negligible.
VO: All the Forensic Science
Service has to work with is
the women's hair.
Stewart PTC: They go through
a process of continual washes
to cleanse the hair, to get rid
of all the debris that
of course will have gathered
through being in the stream.
It was somewhere in the region
of two kilos of debris
that was recovered.
VO: Within the debris
the forensic team find
the tiniest but most
crucial fragments of evidence.
Stewart PTC: From Tania they
recovered just one or two carpet
fibres that matched the
carpet in the footwell of
Steve Wright's Ford Mondeo.
Tania's head at some point
has been in contact with the
footwell of his car.
There were fibres recovered from
Gemma's head hair that again
matched back to
come of Steve Wright's clothing.
We could demonstrate a
link through fibre transference
between all five
victims and Wright.
VO: As the forensic evidence
builds detectives dig deeper
into Steve Wright's background.
Stewart PTC: He was a bit of
a Jekyll and Hyde it would seem.
At face
value quite an ordinary man.
Steve Wright: There was
certainly a history
of domestic violence.
He had a record
of, went back some decades,
of using prostitutes.
And he was a regular user
of street workers within the
Ipswich area.
VO: Eleven months after
the funerals of Gemma, Tania,
Anneli, Annette and Paula,
Steve Wright appears at
Ipswich Crown Court
to be tried for their murders
Stewart PTC: I think we were
feeling reasonably confident.
Without being complacent.
We knew we had a strong case,
but of course until proceedings
are concluded and the jury
return a verdict you
can never be sure.
VO: It takes fifteen days
just to present all the evidence
against Steve Wright.
Reporter: Wright admitted
that he had had sex
with four of his victims.
But during cross-examination
he claimed it was just a
coincidence, giving this same
explanation fifty-three times.
Steve Wright: Stewart PTC: His
broad defence was that he'd been
with all the victims so yes,
of course you'll find traces
of my DNA but I'm not
responsible for murdering them.
VO: After a six-week trial
the jury take just six hours
to decide their verdict.
Stewart PTC: The adrenaline
was flowing fairly high,
the blood pressure was up.
I'm sure, I think
my hands were shaking
and my heart was pounding.
And whilst we thought we had a
strong case we couldn't be sure.
Trevor Macdonald: The man
on trial for the murder of five
women who worked as prostitutes
in Ipswich was today found
Guilty on all counts.
Kirsty Wark: The serial killer
embarked on one of the most
intensive killing sprees
in British criminal history.
News footage: The murders
of these vulnerable young women
left five families devastated.
Our sympathies are
clearly with them at this time.
What I hope is today's Guilty
verdict on their killer brings a
little comfort to them.
Stewart PTC: Steve Wright
was very close and personal with
these young women when they
were at their most vulnerable,
and maybe it was the fact that
he had life and death in his,
his hands.
Stewart PTC: Ultimately the
only man that knows why he did
what he did is Steve Wright.
VO: Fifteen months after his
killing spree began Steve Wright
returns to Court.
Reporter: The man found Guilty
of murdering five young women
who were working as prostitutes
in Ipswich is to spend the rest
of his life in prison.
Steve Wright was told his
carefully planned campaign of
murder meant that he would
never be eligible for parole.
Stewart PTC: He
will never come out of custody,
which I think is,
is right and proper.
Stewart PTC: The families,
they'll never be able to get
over the loss of
their loved ones in such tragic
circumstances.
But knowing that the man
responsible will never see the
light of day again hopefully
provides for some solace.
Isabella Clennell Mother of
Paula Clennell: No parent should
have to bury their child.
No parent.
It was devastating
beyond belief.
This sort of thing
shouldn't happen to anyone.
Not just Paula.
She was helpless,
homeless, penniless.
The girls
on the street, all five of them,
had the same sort
of lifestyle and, er,
people just looked down their
nose at them and ...
I mean, I used
to ask Paula why did she do it.
And she would say 'Mum,
because I'm a heroin addict'.
She was
a fair good lass, lovely girl.
I miss her dearly.
Stewart PTC: I can't remember
another case of its nature.
The scale, the speed,
the magnitude, the coverage,
the exposure.
Of course
it's left its indelible mark.
I found myself in a place
that I never expected to be.
Hopefully never to be repeated.